<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. Walker's invisible champion foyl'd, or, An appendix to the late Narrative of the siege of Derry wherein all the arguments offered in a late pamphlet to prove it a false libel, are examin'd and refuted / by John Mackenzie ...</title>
            <author>Mackenzie, John, 1648?-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11818</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13119904</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13119904</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50929)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 427:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dr. Walker's invisible champion foyl'd, or, An appendix to the late Narrative of the siege of Derry wherein all the arguments offered in a late pamphlet to prove it a false libel, are examin'd and refuted / by John Mackenzie ...</title>
                  <author>Mackenzie, John, 1648?-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The late pamphlet is attributed to Joseph Wilkinson Clark. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walker, George, 1645?-1690. --  Siege of Londonderry in 1689.</term>
               <term>Mackenzie, John, 1648?-1696. --  Narrative of the siege of London-Derry.</term>
               <term>Clark, Joseph Wilkinson. --  Mr. John Mackenzyes narrative of the siege of London-Derry, a false libel.</term>
               <term>Londonderry (Northern Ireland) --  History --  Siege, 1688-1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr. Walker's</hi> Inviſible Champion FOYL'D: OR, AN APPENDIX To the late Narrative of the Siege of Derry: WHEREIN All the Arguments offered in a late Pamphlet to prove it a Falſe LIBEL, are EXAMIN'D and REFUTED.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN MACKENZIE,</hi> Publiſher of the ſaid Narrative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97821:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97821:2"/>
            <head>Dr. <hi>WALKER</hi>'s <hi>Inviſible Champion</hi> FOYL'D, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Am ſorry to find Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Reputation ſunk ſo low, that his Friend who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes his Defence, dare not publiſh his Name. For ſince he dare not, and yet makes ſo bold with other Mens Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he looks much more like a Libeller than one who by owning what he writes, renders himſelf accountable to the Publick for the Truth of it. And if I may make any conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture about my Accuſer, either from this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous Practice, or from his admirable Style and Humour (which are all of a piece with it,) 'tis the ſame Gentleman that wrote Remarks on Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindication: But I fear he will have as little ſucceſs in diſproving what he calls a Libel againſt Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> as he had in juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or rather palliating the Doctors real Libel againſt Mr. <hi>Osborn:</hi> And as Mr. <hi>B.</hi> was better employed than to throw away his time in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing ſuch a heap of falſhoods as his former Scribble contain'd, dreſs'd up in a medley of <hi>Grub-ſtreet</hi> and <hi>Billings-gate,</hi> ſo ſhou'd I have ſerv'd this, if he had not endeavour'd to amuſe the World with ſome ſhew of Proof for the few things he has to ſay againſt my Narrative.</p>
            <p>'Tis no inconſiderable Argument of the Truth of that Relation, that one whoſe Inclination and Intereſt led him to take ſo much pains to blaſt the Credit of it, has produc'd no greater Objections againſt it. There being not above two or three paſſages, and only one of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Narrative it ſelf that he ventures to nibble at: For the greateſt part of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Shot is ſpent againſt a paſſage or two in the Preface, where he tells us the Venom lies. But how little execution he has done ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the Preface, or on the Narrative, will appear by a particular examination of all that's material in his Certificates about 'em: For the ſcurrilous Humour which he will needs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any occaſion given him vent againſt Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I think it unworthy of my notice.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid in the Preface to my Narrative, That that part of it which gives an Account of the Siege of <hi>Derry</hi> it ſelf, was offer'd by me to be review'd by ſuch of the Officers of <hi>Derry</hi> as are now in Town, ſeveral of whom, as Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Crofton,</hi> Collonel <hi>Murray,</hi> Lieutenant Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Blair,</hi> Capt. <hi>Alexander Sanderſon,</hi> &amp;c. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard it read in the preſence of Sir <hi>Arthur Rawdon,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Langford,</hi> Collonel <hi>Upton,</hi> and ſeveral other Gentlemen, and being deſir'd upon every material Paragraph to object againſt any thing either miſrepreſented or omitted in that Relation, freely profeſs'd their aſſent to it.</p>
            <p>Here are two things aſſerted, That that part of the Narrative was offer'd to be review'd by ſuch of the Officers of <hi>Derry</hi> as were then in Town: And that ſeveral of 'em, particularly thoſe named, had heard it read, and freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd their Aſſent to it.</p>
            <p>Againſt which, after abundance of ſuch lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as is ſuitable to his Breeding, he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces three Certificates; and I doubt not but he may obtain many more of the ſame kind from the like Perſons.</p>
            <p>Againſt the former Aſſertion he brings a Certificate of 17. called <hi>Derry</hi> Officers, then in Town, who declare, <hi>They never ſaw my Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive before it was printed, and do not now approve of it,</hi> p. 3. 4.</p>
            <p>Now if he pleaſe to put on his Spectacles, and compare the words of the Preface with thoſe of this Certificate a little better, He may perhaps be able to diſcern, that the contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97821:3"/>betwixt 'em lay only in his Imagination, That it might be offer'd to be review'd by thoſe who had not leiſure or inclination to be preſent at the reading of it. And that it was <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tually offer'd to be review'd by the Chief Officers of the Regiments he mentions; and that they were deſir'd to bring any others with 'em that they thought capable of giving me any Information, appears by the following Certificate.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>WE whoſe Names are ſubſcribed, do hereby Certiſie, That on the <hi>28th</hi> of <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt, we conſented and agreed with Coll. <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray,</hi> Coll. <hi>Hamil,</hi> Lieutenant Coll. <hi>Blair,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> to meet at the <hi>Fountain</hi> Tavern in the <hi>Strand</hi> on the next day, being the firſt of <hi>March,</hi> to peruſe that part of Mr. <hi>Mackenzie</hi>'s Narrative which related to the Siege of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and deſired the ſaid Gentlemen to inform Coll. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and any other Officers they knew in <hi>London,</hi> that were capable to give any account of the ſaid Seige, all which Perſons might have liberty to hear the ſaid Account, and be admitted to make any objections thereto before it was printed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Witneſs our hands <date>this <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>May, 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Art. Langford. Will. Conyngham.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And now let the Reader judge, whether the everlaſting Shame with which he wou'd charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly brand me on this occaſion, be not much more due to his Ignorance or Malice, or both. I wou'd here only add, That whether theſe 17 Perſons mention'd in this Certificate approve the Narrative or no, I think my ſelf little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, unleſs they had ſhew'd me any miſtakes in it. Some of 'em it may be did very good Service; but for others of em perhaps they may diſlike it, becauſe it makes no more mention of themſelves: But that was not any defect of mine, but their misfortune, in having done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more memorable; beſides, ſome of them are not in the liſt of Officers, which I had from the only Store-keeper: But it is fit to return them as ſuch, that they may do ſome ſervice.</p>
            <p>Againſt the latter Aſſertion he produces two Certificates, one of Collonel <hi>Crofton</hi>'s, that I did not read all that part that related to <hi>Derry,</hi> (he ſhou'd have ſaid the Siege of <hi>Derry,</hi>) and that he objected ſeveral things againſt it, and does not aſſent to, or approve of it. Another of Captain <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s, that he did not aſſent to two particulars <hi>viz.</hi> The Articles againſt Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> and the diſcouraging Sermon, not knowing any thing of 'em.</p>
            <p>For Captain <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Certificate, 'Tis no way contradictory to the true intent of the Prë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, which in aſſerting their Aſſent to the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, cannot be reaſonably thought to imply, they perſonally knew the Truth of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular related in it. 'Tis ſufficient that there was no paſſage they cou'd object againſt the Truth of: But how little regard is due to either of theſe Certificates, ſo far as they contradict what is ſaid in the Preface to the Narrative, will appear by the Teſtimony of the following Gentlemen then preſent, whoſe Credit muſt be allow'd by all that know 'em ſufficient to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poize theirs in this matter.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>WE whoſe Names are ſubſcribed, do Certifie, That that part of Mr. <hi>John Mackenzie</hi>'s Narrative, which relates to the Siege of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> (particularly the paſſages now controverted in the Pamphlet, intituled, Mr. <hi>Mackenzie</hi>'s Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative a falſe Libel) was (before the printing of it) on the firſt of <hi>March</hi> last, at the <hi>Fountain</hi> Tavern in the <hi>Strand,</hi> read in our preſence and hearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Coll. <hi>Murray,</hi> Coll. <hi>Crofton,</hi> Lieutenant Coll. <hi>Blair,</hi> Captain <hi>Alexander Sanderſon,</hi> and Captain <hi>Samuel Murray,</hi> late Officers at <hi>Derry,</hi> who being frequently deſired and urged while it was a reading to object freely againſt any thing either miſrepreſented or omitted in that Relation; and to that purpoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſtops and pauſes being made at the end of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Paragraphs, told us that where they made no Objection, we might take it for their aſſent to what was read, and accordingly there were but two or three paſſages about which any doubt was raiſed, and even as to thoſe, the Objectors upon hearing the Debates about them, acquieſc'd in the Evidence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by others for the truth of them; particularly Coll. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and Captain <hi>Sanderſon</hi> owned the change of the Government <hi>(page 30.)</hi> to be truly repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the former alſo owned that there were ſuch Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> and the latter denyed not his having heard frequently of them.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under our hands <date>this <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>May, 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Jo. Cuningham.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Arth. Rawdon.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Art. Langford.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Arthur Upton.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>David Cairnes,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sam. Bull.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>W. Cuningham.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Joh. Abernethy</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>J. Boyſe.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I muſt add, That this Certificate from Coll. <hi>Crofton</hi> is the more ſtrange, becauſe he not only confirm'd what is ſaid of Coll. <hi>Lundy,</hi> Dr. <hi>W.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97821:3"/>and Major. General <hi>Kirk,</hi> which he has alſo ſince own'd before Serjeant <hi>Osborn,</hi> and other Gentlemen, but acquainted us with ſome paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that on his Information were inſerted: Nor do any then preſent remember any material Objections he made, except one, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Meeting, (which at Coll. <hi>Lundy</hi>'s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions ſign'd a Paper of Surrender) being call'd a Council; but he cou'd not deny what is ſaid of 'em to be true; and whatever Names he wou'd now aſſign 'em, they then call'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Council. And now for the civil Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, of a Spirit of Lying, braſſy Impudence, bold Aſſeverations, groſs Prevarication, ſtudied and deliberate Lye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which this Pamphleteer uſes on this occaſion; the Reader will better underſtand where to apply it.</p>
            <p>For the Articles againſt Dr. <hi>W.</hi> I need no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtance of this Gentleman's extraordinary Confidence, than his ſaying they were never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited but in my Narrative. 'Tis a ſign he is an entire Stranger to <hi>Derry,</hi> that has the face to deny what was ſo publickly known there, and there are yet ſo many living Witneſſes of. But as this Advocate of Dr. <hi>W</hi>—'s, has ſaid nothing to diſprove the Articles themſelves, ſo his big words about 'em do not much affright me. Dr. <hi>W.</hi> will I ſuppoſe be wiſer than to offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a fair Trial upon 'em; And whether in ſuch a Trial he be cleared or caſt, concerns not the truth of my Narrative, which only affirms ſuch Articles were drawn up, and a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble number of Officers engaged to proſecute him upon 'em, till Governour <hi>Baker</hi> diverted 'em, by offering to put the Government into the hands of the Council of 14. whereof he was made Preſident: And 'tis not probable, they would undertake to bring ſuch a charge againſt him without ſtrong preſumptions of the Truth of it.</p>
            <p>The next thing which this Pamphleteer falls upon, is to prove Dr. <hi>W.</hi> Governour of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon as well as the Stores: That he was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Stores, and therein Aſſiſtant to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour <hi>Baker,</hi> is aſſerted in the Narrative, and no way denyed in the Preface: But that the care of the Military Affairs of the Garriſon was committed to him, or that he ſhewed himſelf a <hi>Hero</hi> in the management of 'em, is not aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Narrative, becauſe it is not true, and therefore the Preface does but juſtly expoſe his pretenoſins to it.</p>
            <p>Now to prove Dr. <hi>W.</hi> Governour of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, as to the Military Affairs of it as well as Governour of the Stores: Here are 3 Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates produc'd, one ſign'd by 17, call'd <hi>Derry</hi>-Officers, another by Captain <hi>Bennet,</hi> and a <hi>3d</hi> by Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> (whom he calls the preſent Mayor.)</p>
            <p>On which I need only make the following Reflections, to ſhew the inſufficiency of 'em, to the end for which they are brought.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He has not (tho great pains were taken to that purpoſe) produc'd the Teſtemony of one Officer for what he aſſerts concerning Dr. <hi>W</hi>'s. being choſen Governour, that was preſent to vote at the Election of Governour <hi>Baker</hi> on the <hi>19th</hi> of <hi>April.</hi> For Collonel <hi>Crofton,</hi> I can ſhew him a Paper under his own hand, wherein he affirms that Collonel <hi>Baker</hi> was ſole Governour of the Garriſon. What Lieutenant Coll. <hi>Blair</hi> has ſaid of that matter, will appear in its due place: And for Collonel <hi>Murray,</hi> he did to the Doctors Face deny him to have been Governour of the Garriſon, before the Committe of his Majeſties Privy Council, Coll. <hi>Hamil,</hi> and Lieut. Coll. <hi>Blair,</hi> being then preſent, and not offering to contradict what he ſaid, tho the Dr. made his appeal to 'em. And ſure theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen that ſign this Certificate, cannot pretend to know that matter better than thoſe who were preſent when it was tranſacted. And even ſome of theſe very Perſons have frequently declared the quite contrary to what they here certifie, as Capt. <hi>Macullogh,</hi> Capt. <hi>Watſon,</hi> &amp;c. ſo little regard is due to their Aſſertions, who are ſo little conſtant to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis ſtrange that neither theſe 17 Perſons nor the Pamphleteer for 'em, ſhould offer the leaſt ſyllable to invalidate the Truth of thoſe matters of fact which plainly overthrow what they here certifie.</p>
            <p>I might upon a little more leiſure have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd the Teſtimonies of more of thoſe preſent at Governour <hi>Bakers</hi> Election, for the Truth of what is there related; but I need 'em not while the matters of Fact there mentioned ſtand uncontradicted. 'Tis ſtrange that Dr. <hi>W.</hi> ſhou'd be choſen Governour of the Garriſon, and the Military Affairs of it, when he did not ſo much as ſtand a Candidate with Coll. <hi>Baker,</hi> and the other two Competitors; nay when he was not ſo much as preſent till after Coll. <hi>Baker</hi> was elected Governour, and the Regiments were concluded on: And as it is in it ſelf a moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable thing, that they ſhould in their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, while their Safety entirely depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on their Union, ſet up two Governours en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with equal Power, and much more that they ſhou'd commit the Military Affairs to one who they knew cou'd not pretend to the leaſt Skill or Conduct in 'em; ſo the falſhood of it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97821:4"/>is evident from the very reaſon alledged by Coll. <hi>Baker</hi> for deſiring an Aſſiſtant, and from what he ſpoke on that occaſion, and from the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of his Aſſiſtant being left to himſelf. Beſides the frequent Attempts of Dr. <hi>W.</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume more to himſelf, and the vehement oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition he ſtill met with in all of 'em,<note n="*">
                  <hi>See Narrat.</hi> P. 37, 38. 44.</note> plainly ſhew the Vanity of his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: For if he was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Garriſon, he was ſuch a one whoſe Authority was ſo very inſignificant and contemptible in it, that were it not for the liberal Reward that Name has ſo luckily produc'd him, he had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter never laid any claim to it: But with the good leave of the Writer of the Epiſtle, annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the end of that Pamphlet, theſe paſſages do not meerly prove that <hi>his Government was oppoſed,</hi> as he wou'd now gladly colour the matter, but that his pretenſions to the Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of it were rejected with diſdain by the major part of the Garriſon, who were forc'd by ſuch rude treatment to check his buſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Humour, in incermedling with more than belong'd to his Province.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis yet more ſtrange, That theſe 17 Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhou'd never acquaint us with the manner of his being choſen Governour as to the Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Affairs, nor give us the leaſt Inſtance of one thing done by him in purſuance of his Truſt as ſuch a Governour.</p>
            <p>Theſe 17 Perſons ſpeak not one ſyllable of the manner of his being choſen Governour: But perhaps that defect may be thought abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſupplied in the Certificate of <hi>Gervaſe Squire,</hi> Eſq which I ſhall ſet down at length, that what I ſhall offer to invalidate it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the more plain and unexceptionable.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> Do hereby Certifie, that Dr. <hi>George Walker,</hi> during all the time of the Siege of the City of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> and until Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> came into the ſaid City, executed the Office and Place of Governour of the ſame joynt with Collonel <hi>Henry Baker,</hi> until the ſaid <hi>Bakers</hi> ſckning (of which he diel) and after with Collonel <hi>Job. Mitchel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> who was in a general meeting of the Field, and other Officers of the ſaid Garriſon, elected to act as Governour in the ſaid <hi>Bakers</hi> place, (during his ſickneſs) as well in all things relating to Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Affairs, as in ſeeing the Proviſions gathered and distributed; the management of the Proviſions to the best advantage, was a great means by which the ſaid City held out ſo long: And I do alſo certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that it being agreed upon by the ſaid Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Council, that I ſhould adminiſter an Oath of Fidelity (then agreed upon to be taken by the ſaid Governours and Council,) I adminiſtred the ſaid Oath to the ſaid Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> and Coll. <hi>Baker,</hi> as Governours of the ſaid City (the ſaid Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> having the Precedency) as well as to the Members of the ſaid Council, all which I am ready to depoſe upon Oath, if required: And I do further certifie, that I never ſaw a Pamphlet entituled, A Narrative of the Siege of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> or any part of it, publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Mr. <hi>John Mackenzie,</hi> until after it was printed; and having peruſed it ſince, I do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Witneſs my hand <date>the <hi>9th</hi> day of <hi>April, 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Ger. Squire,</hi> Mayor.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall not now inſiſt on it, That as Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> was not then Mayor of that City; ſo his Reputation is not of ſo great weight as this Pamphleteer wou'd in kindneſs to Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> make it: But I ſhall by clearing thoſe matters of Fact which this Certificate gives a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Account of, ſhew its weakneſs and falſhood.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe the Reader muſt know, That neither Coll. <hi>Baker,</hi> nor Dr. <hi>W.</hi> were ſworn at all at the time of their Election, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>19th</hi> day of <hi>April,</hi> (nor indeed any of thoſe that were then made Collonels.) The occaſion of their being ſworn was this: The greateſt part of the Officers in the Garriſon were in <hi>May</hi> extreamly jealous of the Treacherous Deſigns of Dr. <hi>W.</hi> and to a high degree diſguſted with Governour <hi>Baker</hi> himſelf for giving ſo much ear to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of one, of whoſe Integrity they had ſo deep a ſuſpition. Governour <hi>Baker</hi> to remove all occaſion of their ſears, and give them full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in that matter, agreed to the Motion of putting the Government into the hands of a Council of 14. of which they were contented Governour <hi>Baker</hi> ſhou'd be the Preſident, (eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Regiment deputing one to ſit in it, and both City and Countrey having ſome to repreſent 'em.) And if Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> had pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us what the Oath was which he admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, it wou'd have clear'd the whole Affair. For it was no more than this, <hi>That they ſhou'd be true to the Garriſon, and have no Treaty with the Enemy, without the Knowledge and Order of that Council.</hi> Nor was there any difference in the Oath as taken by Governour <hi>Baker,</hi> by Dr. <hi>W.</hi> or any other Member of that Council. Now when this Council of 14. had the Government put into their hands, when Coll. <hi>Baker</hi> was the only Preſident of it, when Dr. <hi>W.</hi> had no more power than any other Member in it (his Concern in the Stores except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97821:4"/>when the Oath Adminiſtred to all of 'em was the ſame, with what face can this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man pretend to have Adminiſtred this Oath to Governour <hi>Baker</hi> and Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> as Governours of the ſaid City: Nay, to have allow'd D. <hi>Walker</hi> the Precedency, who was not Preſident of the Council? For if he were ſworn firſt in theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, it could be no other than a meer complement paid to his gown; for the preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was evidently due to Coll. <hi>Baker,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> cou'd not (whatever he might intend) by Adminiſtring that Oath to Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> make him any more a Governour of the Garriſon, than each Member of that Council might as juſtly pretend to be. Note here, that Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> in this Certificate mentions not one word of Dr. <hi>Walkers</hi> being choſen Governour.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid ſo much to Mr. <hi>Squire</hi>'s, I need ſay the leſs to Capt. <hi>Bennet</hi>'s Certificate. For not to mention the Obſcurity of his Expreſſions concerning Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Governourſhip, 'tis ſtrange that he ſhou'd not only inſinuate that Collonel <hi>Baker</hi> and Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> were Sworn at the time of their Election; but that this was during his ſtay there, both which are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly falſe. The Election was on the <hi>19th.</hi> of <hi>April:</hi> The Oath was Adminiſtred about the latter end of <hi>May;</hi> And both by Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Account, and the Relation that's ſaid to be publiſh't by himſelf, Captain <hi>Bennet</hi> left <hi>Derry</hi> about <hi>23d.</hi> or <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>April.</hi> And ſo inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant is his Certificate, as well as falſe, that were all true that he ſaith concerning Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> ſigning any Writings with Collonel <hi>Baker</hi> to Lieutenant General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> or giving him a little Money to bear his Charges, or being call'd a Governour in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army: 'Tis all conſiſtent enough with his being Governour of the Stores only, if we conſider his forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Collonel <hi>Baker</hi>'s Complaiſance. And Captain <hi>Bennet</hi> might by theſe weak Arguments, be as eaſily led to fancy that Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> was choſen Governour of the Garriſon, as he was that Collonel <hi>Murray</hi> was choſen the General of their Forces, becauſe he uſually led 'em out in their Sallyes, as is aſſerted in the printed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which is known to be Mr. <hi>Bennet</hi>'s. But that the Reader may the better conjecture what it was indeed that moved Captain <hi>Bennet</hi> to Sign ſuch a paper for Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> do but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the following Certificate from two of <hi>Derry</hi> Officers.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>WE whoſe Names are Subſcribed, do Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that about the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Company with Captain <hi>Joſeph Bennet</hi> in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Diſcourſing about his and our going for <hi>Ireland,</hi> he demanded whether we had own'd or approv'd of Mr. <hi>John Mackenzies</hi> Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of the Siege of <hi>London-derry,</hi> declaring to us, that if we did, we-needed not go for <hi>Ireland</hi> with any expectation of Imployment in the Army there; nor any who would not expreſs their diſlike or diſapproving of the ſame, by reaſon of Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Kirks</hi> and Doctor <hi>Walkers</hi> Influence there, or words to that purpoſe.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>As witneſs our Hands <date>this <hi>12th.</hi> Day of <hi>June. 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Samuel Murray. Alexander Heron.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And as none of the Certificates alledge any thing done by Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> as Governour in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Military Affairs, ſo I wou'd deſire his Advocate to give us ſome Inſtances of that kind, which methinks 'twere an eaſie matter to have done, if his pretenſions were true. For I hope they will not allow him to have been a meer Cypher in that Station; And a few ſuch Inſtances would have ſignified more than all theſe Certificates. And one would think, as my Narrative mentions, ſo many things done by Collonel <hi>Baker</hi> as plainly ſhew, that he had the Conduct of their Military Affairs: So Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> account ſhou'd furniſh us with the like Evidence of his ſharing with him in that part of the Government. I have to that purpoſe review'd his Narrative, and ſhall (to ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate for once) take the pains to examine all the paſſages that give the leaſt ground to imagine that the Military Affairs of the Garriſon were under his Conduct.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 21. of Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Account, 'tis ſaid, the Governours divide the Outline into 8 parts, and each Regiment had it's own ground, and each Company knew their own Baſtion — The Drummers were enjoyn'd to quarter in one Houſe.</p>
            <p>Now the Diviſion of the Outline was made by the Officers themſelves; and the quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Drummers in one Houſe, was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of Governour <hi>Mitchelburn,</hi> and that not till the laſt Month of the Siege. And the enjoyning all parties to forget their Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to betake themſelves to their ſeveral Devotions, mentioned in the ſame page, was an Order I never heard of in <hi>Derry:</hi> But thoſe who have ſo liberally given Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> the Conduct of our Military Affairs, might very well (to carry on the Humour) give him the Conduct of our Eccleſiaſtical too, and make him Biſhop, as well as Governour of the City.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 24. Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> is ſaid to have found it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97821:5"/>neceſſary to Mount one of the Horſes, to make our flying Horſe rally, and to relieve Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Murray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now tho' this grand Feat it ſelf be no very-convincing Argument of his Governourſhip; becauſe it might be done by him as Collonel of a Regiment, (it being more proper for a Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, than a Governour to expoſe himſelf to ſo Eminent hazards) yet the Credit of it is much more ſpoyl'd by the unhappy Diſputes that have ariſen about the matter of Fact. For ſome have ſtarted ſuch croſs queſtions about the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Rider, as well as the Colour of the Horſe, as I fear will go near to diſmount the Doctor in the next Edition of that Account, and leave Collonel <hi>Murray</hi> to get off as well as he can without him.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 26. Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> is ſaid to draw a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment of 10 Men out of each Company, and (after putting 'em into the beſt order their impatience could allow) to Sally out at the Head of them, with all imaginable ſilence at <hi>Ferry-key-gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I have heard indeed, that Governour <hi>Baker</hi> and other Officers were about to Detach ſuch a number of every Company; But the Souldiers were too eager to wait any of thoſe Formalities, and ran out in what order beſt pleas'd themſelves. But I never was inform'd before, that Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> was ſo fooliſhly prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of his Life, as to Sally out at the Head of 'em: For if he did ſo, it was not only with all imaginable ſilence, but with ſo wonderful Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy too, as to be neither ſeen nor heard by any of thoſe that are ſaid to follow him. No he underſtood his Poſt in the Stores too well to expoſe his perſon in any of the Sallyes. And therefore the Gentleman that wrote the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his Account might have ſpar'd that long and Learned Apology he has made for the Doctor, as if in the Siege he had been fore't to do ſo many things inconſiſtent with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Clergyman. For as to the Enemy, he was a Man of Peace all the time, and was guilty of Shedding no other Blood to Stain his Coat with, but that of the grape.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 26. Tis ſaid the Enemy hung out a white Flag, to invite us to a Treaty, and Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> ventur'd out to come within hearing of the Lord of <hi>Louth</hi> and Collonel <hi>Oneal,</hi> and in his paſſage, had 100 ſhot fir'd at him, but he got the ſhelter of a Houſe, and upbraided 'em with this perfidious dealing, and bid 'em order their Men to be quiet, or he would command all the Guns on the Walls to be fir'd at 'em.</p>
            <p>Now beſides that Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> might be ſent on a Treaty without being Governour of the Garriſon, (as ſeveral others were;) I have heard ſome incredulous people ſay, that the ſmoak of the 100 ſhot was as inviſible as the flying of the Bullets; and they could not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine whereabouts the Houſe ſtood (all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Gates, next the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Camp, being pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down) that ſo happily yielded the Doctor a ſafe ſhelter, till he cou'd call to the Men on the Walls to fire the Guns at theſe Treacherous Villains.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 32. 'Tis but barely aſſerted (and without the leaſt ground) that Collonel <hi>Mitchelburn</hi> was appointed during Governour <hi>Baker</hi>'s Sickneſs to Aſſiſt Governour <hi>Walker,</hi> that while the one commanded in the Sallyes, the other might take care of the Town.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, Collonel <hi>Mitchelburn</hi> was Deputed by Governour <hi>Baker</hi> to his own Poſt, and conſequently Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> was only his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant, and as I preſume that Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> will no more pretend to have Commanded in the Sallyes, ſo the Garriſon by this time under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him too well to lay any great ſtreſs on his care of the Town.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 33. 'Tis ſaid by the Contrivance of our Governour and Collonel <hi>Mitchelburn, &amp;c.</hi> we Countermine the Enemy before <hi>Butcher</hi>'s-<hi>Gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a ſign how he minded thoſe Affairs, that talks of our Counter-mining the Enemy: For neither they nor we ever drew a Mine. We did indeed Counter-line 'em, but this was pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Governour <hi>Mitchelburn</hi>'s Contrivance, and 'twas a double injury in Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> at once to rob him of the ſole Honour of that Action, and the Title of Governour too.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 37, 38. There is a pleaſant ſtory about the Suſpitions of the Garriſon concerning Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> occaſioned by ſome Diſcourſe of one Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> whom Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> is ſaid to have confin'd on the account of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the ſtory is ſtrangely miſplac't at the end of the Siege; whereas Captain <hi>Cole</hi> came into Town about the <hi>9th.</hi> or <hi>12th.</hi> of <hi>May:</hi> And he was confin'd by Governour <hi>Baker,</hi> not Mr. <hi>Walker;</hi> and that not for any Diſcourſes againſt Mr. <hi>Walker;</hi> but on Suſpition of his being an Agent for the Enemy, among whom he had been detained for ſome time. And ſo far were the Garriſon from being brought to a better Opinion of Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> by any thing Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> diſcovered (as is here idlely ſuggeſted) that ſoon after in the ſame Month, the Articles againſt him were drawn up.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe are the only paſſages in that Account, that carry any colour of an Argument
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97821:5"/>for Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s being Governour as to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Affairs. And ſure if he was ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, he was not ſo extremely modeſt, but he might have given us ſome true Inſtances of his Military Conduct, eſpecially when he had the confidence to impoſe upon the World ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſtaken ones. Likewiſe the Doctor will have Captain <hi>Darcy</hi> to be priſoner in <hi>Derry,</hi> and one of the Signers of the Letter, with the Lord <hi>Nettervile,</hi> &amp;c. to Lieut. General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the beginning of <hi>July,</hi> when it is certain, the ſaid <hi>Darcy</hi> left <hi>Derry</hi> before <hi>May,</hi> 3 or 4 days, Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> being privy to it.</p>
            <p>And as theſe three Conſiderations are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to blaſt the Credit of theſe three Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, ſo far as they contradict either the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative or the Preface, ſo for the three Letters annext, <hi>viz.</hi> of Captain <hi>Alexander Sanderſons,</hi> Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Blair</hi>'s, and from the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Collonel <hi>Lance</hi>'s Regiment, I ſhall only ſay, that as they were written to Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> to beg his Recommendation of 'em, ſo they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give him the Name of Governour, (which the Narrative owns was often given him, as Collonel <hi>Baker</hi>'s Aſſiſtant in reference to the Stores.) And theſe Letters are not the only Evidence, how fulſom Complements, neceſſity and hope of Preferment (eſpecially hearing that nothing was to be done at Court for them, but by Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Intereſt) has drawn from too many of 'em, to one of whom they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt other thoughts before. For Captain <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Sanderſon,</hi> how particularly he approv'd what the Narrative relates concerning the change of the Government, was before obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Teſtimony of ſuch as were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. For Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Blair,</hi> that the Title of Governour wherewith he Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> was never intended by him any otherwiſe than I have explain'd, appears not only by the foreſaid Teſtimonial, but by the following Certificate alſo.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> do hereby Certifie, that about the <hi>15th.</hi> Day of of <hi>April</hi> laſt, Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Thomas Blair</hi> declar'd to me in the preſence of Mr. <hi>John Mackenzy,</hi> that he was earneſtly Sollicited to Sign a Certificate contradictory to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Macken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie's</hi> Narrative, and was threatned if he refus'd, with the danger he might be expos'd to by Major General <hi>Kirk's,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Walker's</hi> Intereſt, when he return'd to <hi>Ireland:</hi> But he refuſed to Sign any ſuch thing; he added alſo, that though he had in <hi>Ireland</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed two Letters, one of his own, the other with ſome other Officers of his Regiment; wherein they had Complemented Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> with the Title of Governour, in hopes of being by his Intereſt put on the new Eſtabliſhment: Yet he knew, and was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to give it under his Hand, that be acted only as Governour of the Stores.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under my Hand <date>this <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>May. 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>John Abernethy.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And as this Diſcourſe of the Lieut. Collonel's unriddles the whole Myſtery of theſe ſeeming contradictions, in what theſe Gent. write and ſpeak concerning Dr. <hi>W.</hi> ſo it gives a ſhrewd ſpecimen of the Artifices (of Threats as well as Flattery) us'd to ſuppreſs the plain Truth in theſe matters: For that ſuch methods have not been try'd with him alone, appears by ſo many of 'em having chang'd their Note ſoon after they came to this Town.</p>
            <p>For the Arguments to prove Dr. <hi>W</hi>'s Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourſhip from its being own'd by the King, the Parliament, the Privy-Council, <hi>London, Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Glaſgow, Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> I ſhall only add, that as I know not that they have own'd him Governour in any ſuch ſenſe as I have here oppos'd, (<hi>viz.</hi> with reference to the Military Affairs of the Garriſon) ſo if they have done it, 'tis a much ſtronger Proof of that Gentleman's extraordinary Confidence in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſuch a Miſtake on 'em, than of their Weakneſs in believing it at firſt, 'till better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd; but I ſuppoſe if he'll enquire better, he'll find ſeveral of 'em are undeceiv'd, and of another Opinion. And if on the ſcore of this ſmall Trick, and the admirable ſucceſs of it, he will needs compare Dr. <hi>W.</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh Rogue, Spaniſh Guſman,</hi> and <hi>Crafty Clanſy,</hi> he may (as being related to him) uſe the greater freedom with him; but moſt People will beg his Pardon for thinking it ſo great a piece of Wit to lead thoſe who had only his own Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that Matter, and the Account of ſuch as deſignedly abetted him, into that Miſtake concerning him.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for Dr. <hi>W</hi>'s Governourſhip.</p>
            <p>The only material Paſſage that relates to the Narrative of the Siege againſt which the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteer has any thing to except, is the Article againſt Dr. <hi>W.</hi> for Embezelling the Stores, and the Order occaſion'd, thereby that his Note ſhou'd not be accepted by the Store-keepers, unleſs ſign'd by Gov. <hi>Baker</hi> or Major <hi>Adams.</hi> Againſt this he produces a long Certificate of Mr. <hi>Curling</hi>'s, wherein he affirms that Dr. <hi>W.</hi> neither cou'd nor did embezzle the Stores, and he never knew the Dr's Orders diſputed. Now Mr. <hi>Curling</hi> does not underſtand the meaning of that Article; for the Dr. was ſuſpected to have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97821:6"/>embezzled the Stores by diſpoſing of 'em when taken out of private Houſes to his own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, without ever ſuffering 'em to come into the Store-keepers hands. And as my Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive only affirms this to have been one of the Articles, ſo the Officers concern'd in drawing 'em up, thought themſelves capable of proving it, and the Order mention'd was really made on that occaſion; and if Mr. <hi>Curling</hi> himſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw the Dr's Orders diſputed, others as well as my ſelf have ſeveral times ſeen his Note rejected by Mr. <hi>Harvey</hi> on this very Account, that neither Gov. <hi>Baker</hi>'s nor Major <hi>Adams</hi> his Hand were annext to it, and after their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe Governour <hi>Mitchelburn</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>But there is one dangerous Paragraph in that Certificate of Mr. <hi>Curling</hi>'s, which I muſt take notice of, 'tis the laſt, in theſe words: <hi>And laſtly, I do declare that ſome Perſons</hi> (<hi>concern'd in putting out this Pamphlet,</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> The Narrative.] <hi>as I preſume</hi>) <hi>ſince I came to</hi> London, <hi>did come to me, and wou'd have drawn me by great Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to have beſpattered and abuſed the Reputation of the ſaid Dr.</hi> W.</p>
            <p>Upon which Clauſe the Pamphleteer thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults; <q>And do not your Ears tingle? are not your Faces cover'd with a Bluſh, who have plotted, caball'd and contriv'd ſuch a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Libel, and more calumniating Preface, and now to hear that ſome of you have been tampering to pervert Truth, and to add Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornation to Bearing falſe Witneſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a deſperate Charge, but if he that brings it do not bluſh when I have clear'd this matter, it will be only becauſe he has ſteel'd his Fore-head.</p>
            <p>I hope none can be preſum'd a better Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of Mr. <hi>Curling</hi>'s words than Mr. <hi>Curling</hi> himſelf, and what he meant by the Paſſage laſt quoted, will beſt appear by this Certifieate of his own.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I Edward Curling</hi> do hereby Declare, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is mentioned in a Certificate under my hand, dated the <hi>25th.</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> which is inſerted in the Pamphlet entituled <hi>Mr.</hi> John Mackenzie<hi>'s Narrative of the Siege of</hi> London-derry <hi>a falſe Libel,</hi> &amp;c. that ſome Perſons ſince I came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> did come to me, and would have drawn me by great Promiſes to have beſpattered and abuſed the Reputation of Dr. <hi>George Walker,</hi> that all I meant or intended therein, was only a Diſcourſe that one Mr. <hi>Hugh Galibraith</hi> had with me ſoon after I came to this City, touching a certain Letter of Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s, which he was told I had, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten was very earneſt to have ſeen or procured it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſhould be <hi>50</hi> pounds in my way, or words to that effect, in caſe I would procure it for him; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were any other Propoſals or Promiſes made to me by him or any other in that behalf, or towards any other beſpattering or abuſing of Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Reputation, or to have ſworn any thing against him, which was never in the leaſt propoſed to me by any Perſon whatſoever, which I Certifie, as</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Witneſs my Hand <date>this <hi>19th.</hi> day of <hi>May, 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Edw. Curling.</signed>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Witneſs.</hi> Thomas Boulton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Here the Reader may ſee by his own Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the <hi>[ſome Perſons]</hi> mention'd in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Certificate, amount only to [<hi>one Mr.</hi> H. G.] And by the way, Mr. <hi>G.</hi> was no more concern'd in the Publiſhing that Narrative than the Ar. Bp. of <hi>Tuam, George Philips</hi> Eſq or Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi> himſelf: Their drawing him by Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to beſpatter and abuſe the Reputation of Dr. <hi>W.</hi> amounts to no more than Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him to expect ſo much Money for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering up that Letter (which by the way is a very improbable Story, and expreſly deny'd by Mr. <hi>G.</hi> himſelf.)</p>
            <p>And now let the Pamphleteer and the other Gentlemen concern'd in procuring this Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate clear themſelves as well as they can of the guilt of Suborning Mr. <hi>Curling</hi> to expreſs ſo innocent a practice of Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s, as deſiring to obtain a real Letter of ſo conſiderable import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, by ſo ſuſpicious words as theſe; <hi>That ſome Perſons concern'd, as he preſumes, in publiſhing that Narrative, wou'd have drawn him by great Promiſes to have beſpattered and abus'd the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Dr.</hi> W. I am ſure this looks in good earneſt like ſhrewd tampering to pervert Truth.</p>
            <p>But perhaps the Reader may be curious to know what this Letter of Dr. <hi>W</hi>'s was which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> was ſo ſolicitous to procure, and what is become of it; to gratifie him therein, I ſhall give the beſt account I can of it, from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Mr. <hi>Curling,</hi> mention'd in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Certificate, and the rather becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms what is ſaid concerning Dr. <hi>W.</hi> in the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, and ſhews how little regard is due to all the good words Mr. <hi>Curling</hi> has beſtow'd on him in his firſt Certificate.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>WE the Subſcribers do certifie, That on the third of <hi>February</hi> laſt, or thereabout; we heard Mr. <hi>Edward Curling</hi> (who had been in <hi>London-derry</hi> during the Siege) ſay publickly on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97821:6"/>the Exchange, That Mr. <hi>George Walker</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Governour of that Garriſon, but only of the Stores; and be further ſaid, that Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> was a great Rogue and Villain, and had endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to betray the ſaid City into the Enemies Hands: And for that end, had Correſponded with Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General <hi>Richard Hamilton;</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Curling</hi> affirmed, he could prove by a Letter now in his Cuſtody, written by Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> to the ſaid Lieutenant General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the which Letter he offered to ſhew to Mr. <hi>John Mackenzie,</hi> and us the Subſcribers at ſix a Clock that Evening, in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof Mr. <hi>John Mackenzie</hi> and we waited on him at the time and place appointed, and he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly met us, and having ſearched many papers be had in his Portmanteu, found not the Letter, for which he appeared to be much troubled, declaring that he believed that Captain <hi>Godfrey</hi> (to whom he had given the Key of his Portmanteu that morning, to get out ſome Cloaths he had in it) had Stolen the Letter; notwithſtanding the ſaid <hi>Edward Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> very ſolemnly declared, that he fully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Contents of the ſaid Letter, and could prove the ſame by divers that had ſeen it. The Contents of which Letter he ſolemnly Affirmed, were as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>viz. Mr. Walker</hi> firſt excuſed himſelf for not performing his Engagement to the ſaid Lieutenant General, ſhewing that the Mobile were in a great Tumult and Rage againſt him; but he hoped they would be ſoon quieted, faithfully promiſing that he would perform his Engagement, only requeſted the Lieutenant General's Patience for a little time, and that he confidently expected the Lieutenant General would not fail the payment of the five hundred pounds; and the ſecuring his Life and Fortune, and procure King <hi>James's</hi> favour to him. The Contents of this Letter as related here, he promiſed to Swear before any Magiſtrate in the City of <hi>London,</hi> if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. All which was Mr. <hi>Curling</hi>'s own volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Propoſal (neither expected nor deſired by us) upon our firſt meeting with him in <hi>London.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Subſcribed <date>this <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>May. 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>John Abernethy. Hugh Galbraith.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And now unleſs the Letter it ſelf cou'd be produc't, we cannot expect any clearer Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence what the Contents of it were, than theſe two laſt Certificates compar'd together. And as I hope Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Advocate will no more upbraid me with Mr. <hi>Curling</hi>'s Certificate, ſo he muſt thank his own folly (to ſay no worſe) that his ſenſeleſs Triumphs upon it have made it neceſſary to lay open this whole matter, which indeed dos ſufficiently beſpatter, but (if Mr. <hi>Curling</hi> his own Witneſs may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd) dos no way abuſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> injure or wrong the Reputation of Dr. <hi>W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Appendix</hi> relating to Captain <hi>James Hamilton,</hi> and the paſſage concerning him in Sir <hi>Arthur Rawdon</hi>'s Memoirs; I need only quote Sir <hi>Arthur Rawdon</hi>'s own ingenuous Reply in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a perſon of Quality, a Friend of his in Town.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>— There is one Paſſage in that Pamplet, becauſe it belongs ſomething to me, I beg leave to take notice of, which is about <hi>Lundy</hi>'s being ſworn aboard the Ship: In the firſt place I muſt needs ſay, I meant ro particular Reflection on Coll. <hi>James Hamilton,</hi> whoſe forwardneſs every where, eſpecially at <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyfoord,</hi> are too great demonſtrations of his Zeal and Integrity to the Cauſe, to be at all blemiſhed; but as it was matter of Fact, I could not omit it; for being accidentally in that Ship with <hi>Will. Ponſonby</hi> and others, that I have forgot, and <hi>Lundy</hi> coming aboard, after ſome ſmall Diſcourſe we were told they had private Buſineſs, ſo that we withdrew out of the Cabin, and ſtayed above Deck with Capt. <hi>Beverly,</hi> 'till we were wet with rain; what was done in the Cabin in the mean time I know not, nor did I hear 'till next day, that moſt People were diſſatisfied with <hi>Lundy</hi> for refuſing to take the Oath publickly again, thô much preſſed to it, particularly by Coll. <hi>George Philips;</hi> and thô now the excuſe is, that the Mayor was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, yet they found a Protestant Mayor there who Proclaimed the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> namely, Mr. <hi>Campſie.</hi> There is a Mistake of mine taken notice of too in the Book, <hi>viz.</hi> ſaying that the Officers Civil and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was from my not remembring the Inſtructions, which I never heard but once. I find in the Printed Book, inſerted in my Memoirs, <hi>That the Biſhop was by at the Proclaiming the King,</hi> &amp;c. thô I ſuppoſe I meant the Mayor, but the Miſtake is not great, and of no conſequence. I beg your Pardon for this trouble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> —</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Arth. Rawdon.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I ſhall only add here, that as all that Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Rawdon</hi>'s Memoir ſaith about the Swearing of <hi>Lundy,</hi> is, that if he were Sworn, it was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry privately, ſo this may very well conſiſt with the Truth of what Captain <hi>Mervin</hi> and Captain <hi>Corry</hi> Certifie: And yet his refuſing to Swear publickly in thoſe Circumſtances, was a very ſuſpicious ſign of his ill intentions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſtly taken notice of.</p>
            <p>For the grave Letter at the end, I ſee nothing in it of Argument againſt any thing in the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97821:7"/>For ſure 'tis but a ſorry proof of Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s being Governour of the Garriſon, that ſome who were at firſt ſo Charitable as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what he pretended to, altered their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents when better informed; but that this was owing to any miſtake about his perſwaſion, is only an idle fancy of the Writers. But ſure thoſe have little reaſon to complain of Dr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Account being Attributed to the <hi>A. B.</hi> of <hi>T.</hi> who with far greater Confidence, father the Preface to my Narrative on Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and thence take occaſion to ſay whatever their Wit and Malice cou'd ſuggeſt againſt him. But how little either of 'em cou'd furniſh 'em with to his prejudice, appears by what this Pamphleteer has ſaid. For he is forc't here to renew the ſame Accuſation he had brought in the Remarks on Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindication, <hi>viz.</hi> That when Dr. <hi>King</hi> and Dean <hi>Manby</hi> were picqueering he took up a Flail, and threſh'd them both, and while the Dr. was engag'd in a Duel with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Apoſtate from the Proteſtant Religion, he came behind his Back and ſtab'd him, only becauſe he incidentally reflected on that perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereof Mr. <hi>B.</hi> is ambitious to be the Celebrated Champion. And in his Remarks on Mr. <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Vindication, he ſaith, he could tell Mr. <hi>B.</hi> what harm his Book did the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and what uſe the Papiſts made of it againſt the Church at that time.</p>
            <p>Now if this Pamphleteer's paſſion had not blinded his Wit, he wou'd in prudence have conceal'd what caſts ſo unhappy a Reflection on ſome of his own Coat, but can never leſſen the Reputation of Mr. <hi>Boyſe</hi> in the Judgment of any but ſuch ignorant Bigotts as himſelf. For ſince he will bring that matter on the Stage, the plain Truth was this.</p>
            <p>Dean <hi>Manby</hi> printed his Conſiderations, that mov'd him to change his Religion, which were nothing elſe but the old Banter about the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Proteſtant Biſhops and Prieſts reviv'd. Dr. <hi>K.</hi> in his Anſwer, choſe to inſiſt on ſuch principles as were only calculated to defend the Miſſion of the Engliſh Biſhops and their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, but left the Miniſters of other Proteſtant Churches (that had not Biſhops for their Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers) in the lurch: Nay, he laid down ſuch Notions as made Church-Rebels of them, as well as the Diſſenting Miniſters, (whom with their Flocks he expreſly excluded from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church.) Mr. <hi>B.</hi> wrote Reflections on both theſe Papers, wherein he laid down the true and common Notions of Proteſtant Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters about Miſſion, and on thoſe endeavour'd to juſtifie the Reformed Miniſtry abroad, and particularly thoſe at home: And now can this Scribbler have the Impudence to pretend that that Book ſhou'd injure the Proteſtants and give the Papiſts advantage, which vindicates the Miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Miniſters of Proteſtant Churches (thoſe of the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> included as much as any) from the Schiſmatical Principles of the Papiſts on the one hand, that deny the validity of all Proteſtant Orders, and thoſe of Mr. <hi>Dod-well</hi> and his Followers on the other, that deny the validity of any Orders but what are derived from Dioceſan Biſhops. If Mr. <hi>B</hi>—'s Flail did on this occaſion threſh 'em both, it was becauſe both deſerv'd it: Nor did he ſtab Dr. <hi>K.</hi> but rather warded off the ſtab which his unhappy Notions wou'd have given, not only to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but thoſe in <hi>France, Piedmont,</hi> &amp;c. too, and all out of a narrow Zeal for the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I ſhall only add that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> was ſo far from oppoſing any juſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours then uſed to ſtemm the Tide of Popery, that he preach'd as many Sermons againſt it in the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign as perhaps any one Clergyman in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And on this occaſion I can heartily joyn with the Writer of this Epiſtle in his Prayers, that God would rebuke that Spirit of bitterneſs and evil-ſpeaking that expoſes us to the ſcorn of our common Adverſary, and contempt of all: And I cou'd wiſh he had given ſome good Advice of that kind both to this Pamphleteer, and to the A. B. of <hi>T.</hi> who in a Sermon preach'd at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> 1684. and ſince printed, vents his Paſſion in ſuch expreſſions as theſe, <hi>p.</hi> 32. But while I am ſpeaking of theſe things, methinks I hear a Voice ſaying to me, as to the Prophet, <hi>Son of Man, ſeeſt thou what they do, they of the Church of</hi> Rome? <hi>Turn thee yet again, and thou ſhalt ſee greater abominations, A People,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo he goes on to deſcribe the Diſſenters. And ſo <hi>p.</hi> 35, 36. — <hi>In return of all which, I hear her</hi> (ſpeaking of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) <hi>crying out in the words, and with the tears and compaſſion of our Bleſſed Saviour, O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O ye of the Forreign Reformation, how often would I have gathered you under the wings of my Communion, and cover'd or excus'd your defects, but ye wou'd not, but now theſe things are bid from your eyes, and your houſe is left to you deſolate. And O ye of the Domeſtick ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how often would I have gathered you, but ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten have I ſtretcht forth my hands to a gainſaying and diſobedient People:</hi> And the ſame Perſon in a Sermon preach'd at <hi>Bow</hi>-Church, <hi>Oct.</hi> 23. 1689. ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>P. 15. <hi>That Church</hi> (viz. The Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97821:7"/>
               <hi>would gather all the parts of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion under her wings as a Hen doth her Chickens, but they would not: But as ſoon as the Sun ſhines, and the Bird of prey is removed, too many begin again to ſcatter and divide, and quarrel, as if they would pick out their Mothers Eyes, and then one another,</hi> &amp;c. The Reader may obſerve what a Spirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, healing, and moderation is in the Mouth of this great Prophet, as well as what a Spirit of Truth, Ingenuity and Candor is in the mouth of this ignorant and ſcurrilous Pamphleteer.</p>
            <p>For my part, I am not in the leaſt conſcious to my ſelf of having ſaid any thing againſt any Party of Proteſtants: And if ſome have the cunning to intereſt a Party in their Reputation, as if whatever is ſaid to expoſe their Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, were levelled againſt all others that are of their perſwaſion, I cannot help their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes who ſo groſly miſunderſtand the Deſign of my Narrative. But what I have ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning two or three particular Perſons, is no more than what was not only true, but neceſſary to have been ſaid, in giving that plain Account of theſe Tranſactions, which the miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of others gave too juſt occaſion for. And if the Pamphleteer will needs draw that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Inference from my Narrative, <hi rend="margSglQuotes">That all the brave and glorious Actions in the Siege were performed by the Diſſenters, and Coll. <hi>Murray</hi> at the Head of 'em, All inglorious Actions, and treacherous Attempts are to be imputed to the other part of the Garriſon, and principally to Dr. <hi>W.</hi>
               </hi> let him look to his Concluſion, for the premiſes are true: But I confeſs I ſhould deny the Inference, becauſe ſeveral of the Officers that are much commended, were of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> thô but very few of the common Souldiers.</p>
            <p>To ſhew further how little Credit is due to Mr. <hi>Squire</hi>'s Certificate, which the Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer boaſts ſo much of, I ſhall produce Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> to confute himſelf in the following Certificate, though not in its due place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it came but late to my hands.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> Do hereby Certifie that <hi>Gervaſe Squire,</hi> Eſq of the City of <hi>Derry,</hi> did ſoon after his coming over for <hi>England,</hi> upon my enquiry concerning Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> inform me, that he was not Governour of the ſaid City, but Coll. <hi>Baker,</hi> and that he had only the Stores committed to his Truſt.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under my hand <date>this <hi>14th.</hi> Day of <hi>June, 1690.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Gervaſe Byfeld.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhould not have taken notice of another ſmall Miſtake relating to <hi>Derry,</hi> ſuggeſted in Mr. <hi>Walker</hi>'s Narrative, if it had not been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo inſerted in a Letter, ſubſcribed <hi>H. R.</hi> (probably <hi>Hugh Rowley</hi>) ſet down in Mr. <hi>Cox</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Part <hi>2d.</hi> that Mr. <hi>Philips</hi> ſhould have ſent to the Citizens of <hi>Derry</hi> on approach of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces to ſhut their Gates, and that they accordingly did ſo; aſcribing that to him which was inconſiſtent with the Citys Declaration, Letters ſubſcrib'd by himſelf, in my Narrative mention'd, and the Account given by thoſe who were prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally concern'd in that Affair.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid ſo much to clear my Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive from the Aſperſions caſt upon it by this idle Pamphlet, I think fit to deſire the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor if he ſcribble again, to be ſo honeſt as to ſet his Name to it, for I ſhall not think my ſelf concern'd to encounter any longer with Spectres and Hobgoblins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Any Perſon that hath a deſire to ſee the Originals of theſe Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, may find them at my Lodging, at the</hi> Golden Ball <hi>and</hi> Tobacco-roll <hi>in</hi> Clements-lane, <hi>near</hi> Lumbard-ſtreet.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
